Register of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party Records, 1962-1971
Wisconsin Historical Society
Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party Records, 1962-1971
Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party
Mss 586; Micro 788; PH 6705
0.4 c.f. (1 archives box), 3 reels of microfilm (35 mm), and 1 filmstrip (35 mm)
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP) from 1962 to 1971. The collection consists of manuscript and microfilmed documents illustrating the organization of the party, its two challenges and subsequent law suits, its voter registration and community organizing work, and Mississippi politics in general. Included are correspondence and printed mailings, statements, and press releases; legal documents; reports and general papers; the proceedings of the Credentials Committee of the Democratic National Convention; election and registration materials; news clippings; newsletters; materials concerning related organizations; and copies of a masters' thesis and other term papers written about the MFDP by historian Leslie B. McLemore.
The Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP) was officially established at a mass meeting in Jackson, Mississippi on April 26, 1964. The roots of the party originated in the widespread dissatisfaction among Mississippi African Americans who were not recognized by the powerful regular Democratic Party in the state, and who were not permitted to register or to vote. During the campaign preceding the fall 1963 elections, the discontent coalesced and when an unofficial freedom ballot for governor was held, state NAACP chair Aaron Henry received 80,000 votes.
In 1964, MFDP organized a statewide political structure parallel to that of the Mississippi Democratic Party. During the summer, the Freedom Democrats, in conjunction with the Council of Federated Organizations (COFO), registered over 50,000 African Americans. MFDP candidates Victoria Gray, Fannie Lou Hamer, John Cameron, and James Houston, opposed regular Democrats Senator John Stennis, and Representatives Jamie Whitten, William M. Colmer, and John Bell Williams in the Democratic primary of June 2, 1964, but were defeated.
Following this defeat, and an abortive attempt to place the candidates on the ballot as independents, the MFDP initiated the first of two challenges to the regular Democratic Party. During the weeks preceding the Democratic National Convention in August, precinct meetings and county conventions were held throughout the state and delegates were selected to attend the MFDP state convention held on August 6. At the state convention, 68 delegates and alternates were chosen for the National Convention. In Atlantic City, the MFDP delegates challenged the seating of the white Mississippi delegation. Although there was a certain amount of support among state delegations partial to the MFDP challenge, the credentials sub-committee of the Democratic National Committee rejected the MFDP slate. Subsequently, on December 4, 1964, the MFDP challenged the seating of the entire Mississippi delegation to the House of Representatives, on the grounds that the election in November was illegal and unconstitutional, and the results void. The Congressional Challenge also demanded that the three MFDP representatives, Gray, Hamer, and Annie Devine, be seated in the House. This challenge was also defeated, by Congressional vote, on September 17, 1965.
After these two major defeats, party members concentrated their efforts on local and statewide voter registration, demonstrations, civil rights projects, and election campaigns. A massive registration and election campaign held prior to the May 1966 special elections in Sunflower County also failed, as all African Americans and MFDP candidates were defeated. However, the following year Robert Clark was elected as Mississippi's first black representative in nearly a century. The party began to splinter in 1967-1968, and some MFDP members joined with young progressive whites to form the Loyal Democrats of Mississippi. Only in this way were some Mississippi black leaders able to gain the recognition needed to challenge the state's regular Democratic organization. By 1969 and 1970, the MFDP was virtually defunct.
The records, both in paper form and on microfilm, have been arranged in two series: MISSISSIPPI FREEDOM DEMOCRATIC PARTY RECORDS; and MISSISSIPPI GENERAL POLITICS.
The MISSISSIPPI FREEDOM DEMOCRATIC PARTY RECORDS include files of correspondence to and from party chairman Lawrence Guyot, and with the party's attorney, Joseph L. Rauh Jr., the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, and other groups and individuals. There is a folder of organizational papers, with platform statements of MFDP candidates, a few minutes and other documents from the formative stages of the party, and files of general papers containing printed MFDP form letters, reports, news releases, position papers, and copies of the challenges, law suits, and court documents. In addition, there are items received by party headquarters in Jackson or in Washington, D.C., some material on the 1963 freedom ballot, and a few papers regarding the Loyal Democrats of Mississippi, 1967-1968. Also present are copies of formal notices of intention to contest election results, and a copy of the partial proceedings of the Credentials Committee of the Democratic National Convention, including Fannie Lou Hamer's statement.
Records of the Mississippi Summer Project and voters registration campaign of 1964 consist of an incomplete run (last names P-S) of applications to work on the project, supporting letters (which are filed immediately behind the application to which they refer), and a Current Personnel List. These projects were sponsored jointly with COFO. The Freedom Primers and other manuals were published by MFDP as part of its educational work. The Clippings file contains photocopied news clippings from Mississippi newspapers, and from major national papers, especially the New York Times. Within the folder pertaining to Robert Clark's election to the Mississippi House may be found news clippings, campaign documents, and a typewritten paper by David Emmons analyzing the victory. Following a court order voiding the regular election and setting a special May 1966 election in Sunflower County, the MFDP conducted a massive voter education, registration and awareness campaign. These efforts are documented in the files concerning Sunflower County, by news clippings, press releases, flyers, and other mailings. Also included are some records of the National Committee for Free Elections in Sunflower. Leslie B. McLemore's papers include a copy of his 1965 Master's thesis on the MFDP, a paper entitled Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, A Case Study of Grass Roots Politics (1969), and another titled 1967 Sunflower and Mississippi Municipal Elections (1970).
The second series, MISSISSIPPI GENERAL POLITICS, contains printed reference material about state elections, voter registration statistics, state officers, politics, the Democratic Party, and similar material. The writings by McLemore and others consist mainly of notes and drafts. A file on the Young Democratic Clubs of Mississippi includes a few flyers and a report of activities.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Portions loaned for microfilming by Leslie B. McLemore, Jackson, Mississippi, 1979; loaned for copying by Joseph L. Rauh Jr., Washington, D.C., 1979; presented by the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, via Lawrence Guyot, 1967, and via Michael Morgalla, 1975; and transferred from the Social Action Vertical File. M67-226, M67-459, M75-422, M79-510, M79-577
Contents List
- Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party Records
  - Paper Documents, Mss 586
    - Organizational papers, platform statements, 1964-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous minutes and reports, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and mailings, 1964-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Key list mailings, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Papers and reports, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Press releases, 1964-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Public statements and speeches, 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Congressional Challenge, 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Proceedings of the Democratic National Convention Credentials Committee (partial), 1964 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Legal briefs and memoranda, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Formal notices of intention to contest elections, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous legal documents, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Political primers and handbooks, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Election and registration materials, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Memos, leaflets, flyers, and petitions, 1964-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous materials regarding Elections and Politics (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Mississippi Freedom Labor Union, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Miscellany regarding Other Groups, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Freedom Democratic Party Challenge: filmstrip, 1964, PH 6705
  - Microfilmed Documents, Micro 788
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Reel 1, Segment 1)
    - General Papers
      - 1963-1965 (Reel 1, Segment 2)
      - 1965-1971 (Reel 2, Segment 2)
    - Mississippi Summer Project and Voters Registration, 1964 (Reel 2, Segment 3)
    - Freedom primers and other manuals, circa 1965, 1967 (Reel 2, Segment 4)
    - Clippings
      - 1964-1968 (Reel 2, Segment 5)
      - 1968-1970 (Reel 3, Segment 5)
    - Clark, Robert, Election to Mississippi House of Representatives, 1967-1968 (Reel 3, Segment 6)
    - Flyers of other candidates, 1966-1967 (Reel 3, Segment 7)
    - Sunflower County elections, 1965-1967 (Reel 3, Segment 8)
    - The Sunflower County Project report, 1964-1965 (Reel 3, Segment 9)
    - McLemore, Leslie B., Master Thesis, 1965, and Other Papers, 1969, 1970 (Reel 3, Segment 10)
    - MFDP News Letters
      - Nos. 1, 3-6, 8-10; 1965 March 17, April 24, June 5, July 7, 28, September, November 5, December 20 (Reel 3, Segment 11)
      - No. 1; 1967 October 1 (Reel 3, Segment 11)
      - Volume 1?, No. 3; 1967 November 27 (Reel 3, Segment 11)
      - Volume 2, Nos. 2, 4-6, 8, 9, [misnumbered]; 1967 [undated], December 19; 1968, January 30, [undated], June 22, November 5 (Reel 3, Segment 11)
    - Hinds County FDP News
      - Volume 1, Nos. 11, 13, 22, 23, 25, 27-29, 32-34, 37-39, 45; 1967 March 23, April 8, June 10, 16, 30, July 14, 21, 28, August 18, 25, September 1, 23, 29, October 6, 27 (Reel 3, Segment 12)
- Mississippi General Politics (Reel 3, Segment 12)
  - Mississippi voting and voters registration, elections, politics, and reference materials, 1963-1968 (Reel 3, Segment 13)
  - General information, State Officers, 1964-1968 (Reel 3, Segment 14)
  - Election results, 1966-1969 (Reel 3, Segment 15)
  - General information on politics and the Democratic Party - writings of McLemore and others, undated (Reel 3, Segment 16)
  - Young Democratic Clubs of Mississippi, 1965 (Reel 3, Segment 17)